<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from the Palatinate A true and comfortable relation of the wonderfull proceedings of Count Mansfield, from his forst comming into the Palatinate, vntill this present moneth. Wherein to his eternall memory he hath set out Gods glory, and enlarged his owne renowne, by being honest to the King of Bohemia, and a constant maintainer of the Gospell of Christ. Likewise relating the true and admirable manner of raising of the siege of Franckendale by Sir Horatio Vere, with the rest of his proceedings, vntill this present. Faithfully translated and extracted out of a Dutch letter sent from Franckendale, by a great commander, who hath beene an eyewitnesse of the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857362</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857362</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1148:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from the Palatinate A true and comfortable relation of the wonderfull proceedings of Count Mansfield, from his forst comming into the Palatinate, vntill this present moneth. Wherein to his eternall memory he hath set out Gods glory, and enlarged his owne renowne, by being honest to the King of Bohemia, and a constant maintainer of the Gospell of Christ. Likewise relating the true and admirable manner of raising of the siege of Franckendale by Sir Horatio Vere, with the rest of his proceedings, vntill this present. Faithfully translated and extracted out of a Dutch letter sent from Franckendale, by a great commander, who hath beene an eyewitnesse of the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at the Hage [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19132 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626.</term>
               <term>Vere of Tilbury, Horace Vere, --  Baron, 1565-1635.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23086:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newes from the PALATINATE.</p>
            <p>A true and comfortable Relation of the wonderfull proceedings of Count MANSFIELD, from his firſt comming into the PALATINATE, vntill this preſent Moneth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein to his eternall memory he hath ſet out Gods glory, and enlarged his owne renowne, by being honeſt to the King of</hi> BOHEMIA, <hi>and a conſtant maintainer of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe relating the true and admirable manner of raiſing of the fiege of <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckendale</hi> by Sir HORATIO VERE, with the reſt of his proceedings, vntill this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated and extracted out of</hi> a Dutch Letter ſent from <hi>Franckendale,</hi> by a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who hath beene an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Printed at the Hage. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proem">
            <pb facs="tcp:23086:2"/>
            <q>
               <l>Repetunt proprios quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recurſus,</l>
               <l>Reditu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuo ſingula gaudent.</l>
               <l>Nec manet vlli traditus ordo,</l>
               <l>Niſi quod fini iunxerit ortum,</l>
               <l>Stabilem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſui fecerit orbem.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Boetius Metro. 2. lib 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23086:2"/>
            <head>THE VVONDERFVLL PROCEEDINGS AND progreſſes of Count <hi>Mansfield in the</hi> PALATINATE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Muſt needs now remember the returne of the explorators of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> who terrified the people, with a report of Enachims and Giants, yron gates, and high Towers, ſtrong walles, and impregnable Bulwarkes, great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and formidable Soldiours, onely <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> oppoſed themſelues with a contrary diſcouery of a plentifull Countrey, and large inheritance; for which the people had like to haue ſtoned them. Thus haue they dealt with the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> euer ſince the loſſe of <hi>Prague,</hi> and <hi>Spinola's</hi> entring into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> geering and deriding his attempts, as if it were impoſſible to proſecute any enterpriſe againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and withſtand the King of Spaines Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, with ſuch auxiliary Princes, as depend vpon his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty: whereupon they haue not onely ſcorned his Election, but taught their tongues a leſſon of defamation, and their hands a cunning of deciphering his weakeneſſe and temerity, in many calumnious Pictures, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reports, neuer remembring <hi>Ahabs</hi> little cloude, and what an inundation of raine it grew vnto, nor the childrens of <hi>Iſraell</hi> making of Bricke in the Land of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> and what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23086:3"/>a glorious Nation they came vnto, nor the deridings of <hi>Sanbolet</hi> and <hi>Tobias,</hi> when they re-edified the Temple, and how they preuayled in deſpight of oppoſition: nor in a worde, how the Church of God for all the watchings of the Dragon in the Wilderneſſe, hath beene ſtill delinered like that woman, and flouriſhed in the end for all her hard beginnings, and outragious aduerſaries; and why may not time bring foorth the like birth for the happy deliuerance of the Palatinate, and her Maſter, for all this thicke han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging cloud ouer her head, threatning a tempeſt of vtter deſtruction, and deſolation.</p>
            <p>But my meaning is, not to trouble you with repititions, or vnbinde the fardell of tumor, concerning former mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; wherein you ſhall finde her garment be-painted with many tongues on the outſide, and as many hearts on the inſide, to intimate thus much, that men will be talking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſpoſition of their hearts: ſome like Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, ſome like Polliticians, ſome like irreligious Neuters, ſome like Hiſpaniolized inſtruments, ſome like true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and euery one as their fancy induceth: Nay, I will not ſpeake a worde of former preparations, nor how the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> proued ſo good a Seruitour to the Emperour, that vpon his comming into the Palatinate, the Papiſts about <hi>Vdenhem,</hi> in the vpper part of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Spires,</hi> made a Comedy of the loſt King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as they tearmed him, and vſed many vnſeemely ſpeeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in that Interlude, with ſuch vndecencies, that England it ſelfe eſcaped not their ſcandalous minortiues: but it paſſed not away with that ſuccesfull jollity as they pretended, for the comming downe of Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> quickly ſtopped all their mouthes, and quenched the heat of theſe burning reproches; as for thoſe vnſauory vntruths of making compoſition of agreement with the Emperour,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23086:3"/>or Duke of <hi>Bauaria:</hi> there neuer was ſuch a thought, nor motiue, either of reuolt from the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to them, and therefore of him onely and his proceedings, according to the Poet: <hi>Arma virum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vno,</hi> I will now ſpeake, and ſhew you by Gods grace the ſucceſſe of his affaires, and then iudge your ſelues what poſſibility he ſtands in, and whether fairer dayes may come in the ſtead of tempeſtuous weather, yea, I make no queſtion (according to another Poet:)</p>
            <q>Saepe premente Deo fert Deus alter opem.</q>
            <p>The 14 of October 1621. his Excellency, for ſo we muſt ſtile him: or Generall, with his whole Army came out of the vpper Palatinate toward <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>delberg,</hi> being eight Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of foote, containing 108. Companies, and 56. Cornets of Horſe, ſomewhat weake, and wearyed with long Marches, yet were they 10000. ſtrong by Pole: but hearing of the ſiege of <hi>Franckendale,</hi> they ſtayed not long there, as reſoluing to raiſe it, and releeue the Countrey, to which they were the rather animated, becauſe that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Vere</hi> ſent Colonel <hi>Ouertrant</hi> out of <hi>Mainhem,</hi> with fixe Cornets of Horſe, foure Demy Cannons, and two Pieces of ſixe pound bullets vnto him, who were welcommed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and ſo his Excellency with 2000. in his owne Regiment. Colonell <hi>Merſen</hi> with 1200. Colonell <hi>Wald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Hawſen</hi> with 2000. and part of a new Regiment vnder Colonell <hi>Bandſhaw,</hi> being 1000. with foure Pieces more: beſides thoſe which Colonell <hi>Ouertrant</hi> brought, marched preſently to <hi>Franckendale;</hi> but the Enemy hearing of his approach, disbandied themſelues, and left the ſiege, reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring toward <hi>Wormes:</hi> yet firſt poſſeſſing the Bridge, they had made right ouer againſt <hi>Steine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this was not ſo couertly done, but they of <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kendale</hi> had notice of the ſame, and made a braue Salley,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23086:4"/>wherein the Engliſh, whom Generall <hi>Vere</hi> had left in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, there performed their partes like honeſt men, and worthy Soldiers, for there were forty of the Enemy ſlaine, an Italian Captaine with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Enſigne taken priſoners, and many others ouertaken in the flight; by which occaſion they were freed of the ſiege, and deliuered from the feare of vtter deſtruction: For although the Towne was well fortified and had many Bulwarkes and Trenches, which Generall <hi>Vere</hi> before his departure had ouerſeene, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared: yet were they not ſo perfected and warrantable, but ſuch an Army, as the Spaniard had of 9000. at leaſt, might in time either batter, or enforce, conſidering the Gariſon decayed, and prouiſion failed: but God was their protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and as you haue heard, ſent this ſupply to put new life into their courages, and relieue their diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>Now the ſiege of Franckendale was in this manner; the Enemy taking aduantage of Generall <hi>Veres</hi> retiring to Mainhem, came with 9000. before it, and for foure weekes continually battered the Bulwarks; but by reaſon he had not taken in any of the Sconſes, nor diſmantled the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall out-works, he could not endamage the Towne it ſelfe. Nay: when he had valiantly and fortunately got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Counterſcarfe, he was forced out againe with the loſſe of 100. men, and taught to know, that a ſtronger arme putteth out the ſtrong man: yet not altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned, as reſolued, that Honour worketh vpon difficult attempts, he obtained a halfe Moone, from whence he was alſo fiered, and repulſed with the like loſſe: For when we perceiued, that they were Maſters of the ſame, and in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Trenches, we preſently made a Mine, which proſpered ſo well, that we blew them into the ayre: For the Towne hauing a paſſage at the back of the halfe Moon after the faſhion of rauelings, we did the better effect our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23086:4"/>purpoſe, though the worke it ſelfe was quite defaced. There was alſo another halfe Moone ſomewhat leſſe made vpon the ditches, which likewiſe the Enemy attempted; but belike hearing of the failing of the former, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, although they had made many brauadoes to aſſault euen the ditches themſelues, wherein they might haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered their whole Army: For they were ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, that 3000. men could not ſurpriſe them, then had they the wall to come to, which muſt haue endangered them a great deale more: nay, if they had obtained the wall, which muſt be done with the like loſſe: there were many Scafferies behind, and a new wall begun to be made, which alſo would haue much endamaged them: ſo that by the iudgement of experienced Souldiers, and the ſucceſſe of that, wherein they had beene engaged, conſidering they could not bring the Cannon to batter for the out-workes, this Army would queſtionleſſe haue been conſumed in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this one place, and yet they might haue failed to. For in three weekes they loſt 3000. men, and diuers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of account, beſides great Officers and Captaines, whoſe bodies were embalmed and ſent to Stein: but (God be thanked) to preuent our further feare, and vaine ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of what might haue beene done on both ſides, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> preuented all our accounts, and the Enemy departed within foure dayes toward Wormes, ſo that the Generall came not to Franckendale at all, but preſently followed the Enemy to Wormes, and there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped himſelfe round about the 18. of October, whether repaired Generall <hi>Vere,</hi> &amp; ſome Engliſh Captaines, hauing leaſure to treat of their affaires, &amp; ſend to Heidelberg, and other places both to comfort &amp; ſupply them: But the truth is, we determined to ſet vpon the Enemy at his Bridge, had we not found many inconueniences in the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:23086:5"/>
            <p>For as he lay betweene the Rhein and a Marſh, well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched and inſconſed by Stein, wee could not come at him, or if you will, durſt not ſet vpon him, becauſe men were precious vnto vs, and many wants came vpon vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the time of yeere which threatned vs with vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable weather, the Countrey was alſo forraged, and the warres had looked vpon this flouriſhing Prouince, with as angry a countenance, as when ſhe threatned to depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and deſtroy a Countrey indeed: For both the Enemy and our ſelues muſt be here, and now ſupplied: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon his Excellency about the 22. of October reſolued to retire, and diſpierce his Army, and ſo ſome went to Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kendale: ſome returned with Generall <hi>Vere</hi> to Mainhem: both the Colonels <hi>Merſen, Bandſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w</hi> went to Heidelberg, and his Excellency himſelfe departed to Mainhem, but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried not long, by reaſon of many inconueniences: ſo hee obſcured his time, and paſſed ouer the Bridge into the Biſhoprick of Spires, taking all places he came at, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacking euery Town, wherein he determined not to recide except Vdenhem: from thence vnderſtanding of the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der guard of other places, he deuided his Army, ſending ſome forces to Benſhem, ſome to Heppenhem, and ſome to Weinhem, all which he quickly ſurpriſed, taking the ſpoile for his Souldiers, &amp; as quickly forſooke, when the Enemy approched, who indeede watched him very narrowly: Yet Colonell <hi>Tilley</hi> paſſed moſt induſtriouſly to Badenberg, &amp; there made a Bridge ouer the Necker, and raiſed a Sconſe right againſt Neckerhauſen, where he quartred himſelfe, as his Excellency had done in other places, to the refreſhing of his Souldiers, and enriching his Army.</p>
            <p>Till this the Bauarians were at variance with the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, and ſome vnkindneſſe aroſe about Precedency of places: For the Spaniſh Generall <hi>Don Cordona</hi> would not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23086:5"/>giue place to the Bauarians, which Colonell <hi>Tilley</hi> challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as lying neereſt the Enemy, and skirmiſhing often with his Excellency, whereupon they fell to blowes, and that at laſt deuided them aſſunder: ſo the Bauarians going ouer Odenwald, tooke Mosbach, and Ederback on the Necker, and alſo Steinbach, and Schonam, which hee might doe with eaſe, conſidering Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned once againe to Mainhem about the 13. of Nouember, and ſo was this Biſhoprick of Spieres toſſed as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two Seas, and ready to be ſwallowed of either: For both the Armies were needy, and the belly hauing no eares, nor eyes to diſcerne parties, called for meat, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained all that came.</p>
            <p>But what with the neceſſity of his affaires, &amp; the ſtirring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſpirit, his Excellency could not reſt long in a place, &amp; ſo the 15 of Nouem went ouer the Bridge againe, taking in Dieteſhen, which after 8. Cannon ſhot yeelded without reſiſtance, wherein Duke <hi>Saxon Lowanbord</hi> ſtayed with his Regiment. From thence the 16. of Nouember, his Excellency took Keichweild Towne, and a Caſtle ſtanding in a marſh by compoſition: for it ſhould ſeeme both Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and Souldiers (though for the moſt part Subiects of the Biſhoprick of Spires) were well addicted to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and ſo yeelded without battery, making interceſſion to ſerue him, and ſo they were entertained, and remained amongſt vs, &amp; the rather, becauſe the Enemy was ſtrong in theſe parts &amp; places, as lodging the chiefe Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Lipp,</hi> vnder <hi>Graue Rheinhart van Solmes,</hi> with his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and 2000. Horſe vnder the <hi>Saxon Lowanbord,</hi> who were all diſpierſed, for maintainance in the Countrey, and lay thus vpon aduantage to ſet forward the ſeruice.</p>
            <p>The 18. of Nouember we marched toward Lunterbord, taking both the Caſtle and the Towne without reſiſtance.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23086:6"/>For the Inhabitants hearing of our approach, abandoned their dwellings, except 10. Burgers, and the Secretary of the State, who ſubmitted themſelues, and admitted of our preuailing: the reſt of the people fled ſome houre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came, whereby we found much Houſhold-ſtuffe, apparell, and linnen; all which fell to the Souldiers, by his Excellencies appointment, who deſiring rather money, then to be encombred with ſuch vnportable ſtuffe, ſold that for a Florine, which was worth tenne: for when peace and ſafe conduct was proclaimed to all, that would returne, and repoſſeſſe their houſes, many came backe againe and redeemed their furniture at eaſie rates: ſo his Excellency made his chiefe quarter here, and grew ſo ſtrong, that the Townes both of Wormes and Spiers, deſired his Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and paid great ſummes of money, the one was granted, the other receiued; by whoſe example other Townes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended likewiſe to contribution: For Landaw and Weiſenburg, both rickes Townes; disburſed great ſums: Haggenaw paid 5000. ricks dollers, and hath yeelded her ſelfe with the tender of all ſeruice, and the ſupply of his Excellencies wants, eſpecially to ſend him Prouant and Munition, if he went to Lanterburg, yea all the places and people ſubmitted themſelues, and applauded his fidelity and endurances.</p>
            <p>Inſo much, that from the 18. of Nouember, to the 25. there aſſembled ſo great a number of Earles, Barons, Colonels, Captaines, and Gentlemen, beſides the wonderfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe of people, that as it is one way incredible, ſo is it another way remarkable, that either the perſon or the cauſe ſhould thriue ſo ſuddainely, and againſt all expectation: euery man offering his ſeruice to his Excellency, and euery thing giuing waie to his fortunes, and the ſucceſſe of his enterpriſes, <hi>Don Court,</hi> a Baron of Loraine, hath muſtred
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23086:6"/>600. Horſe: Graue <hi>Caſsimire van Loweſtein</hi> 1000. Colonell <hi>Carleſton</hi> 600. Horſe, and to make the Companies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat both with Foot and Horſe, Commiſſions were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about the end of Nouember, to raiſe 6000. Foot more, whereof the moſt part are come already: ſo that in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if multitudes of men will performe any exploit, here are men enough to ouer-runne a Kingdome; or if thoſe men they haue may be paid and kept together, here are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that propoſe great matters to themſelues, and as great ſeruice to their Generall. The Duke of Bulloigne propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth 4000. Foot, and 1000. Horſe. The Prince of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg with diuers great States, and other Ricks Townes promiſe faire, and ſend his Excellency word, they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready 8000. in Armes, and at the Spring will make them vp 15000. for the defence of the Palatinate; and as it ſhould ſeeme, all the Princes of the Vnion, ſomewhat aſhamed of their former retraction, will reaſſume new courages, and make a triall of new fortunes: ſo that by this computation, if we may flatter our ſelues with the hopes of promiſes, and coadiutements of men, ſuch as the Romanes were wont to Auxiliary forces, and Preſidiary Colonies, the King of Bohemia reckoning his own helps, may preſume of 60000. men: but yet farre be it from preſumption, becauſe God worketh many times with leſſer number greater workes, then either the recouery of the Palatinate, or Kingdome of Bohemia.</p>
            <p>To this we may adde that Army which is already vnder the commands of <hi>Iohn George</hi> Marqueſſe of Iaggendorpe, and the Earle of Thorn, being at the leaſt 16000. ſtrong in Bohemia, and the Prouinces of Sileſia and Morauia, for all the threatnings of the Duke of Saxony, and inconſtancy of the Citizens of Prague, and why may I not name the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians, and Tranſiluanians vnder <hi>Bethelem Gabor,</hi> who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23086:7"/>queſtionleſſe will not deale ingenerouſly with the King of Bohemia, but ſtep in as a ſharer in this recouery, and keepe all the contracts in deſpight of rumour, that will haue him at peace with the Emperour, or at leaſt at truce in this time of his abſence from Vienna, as is reported, that he is gone toward Italy about a marriage: But whether it be ſo or no, ſuch be the Letters, ſuch is the report, and euery man ſtands gazing on theſe preparations, as if they were to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſome prodigious comet, falling onely into the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of coniecture, what ſhould be the iſſue of both. For my part I leaue all to the vnſearchable prouidence of God, and returne to the buſineſſe in hand, which turneth me ouer to a new worke.</p>
            <p>By the occaſion of theſe warres, and dilacerating the peace and plenty of Countries, this goodly Prouince of the Palatinate had come into the hands of cruell vſurpers, and vnnaturall ſtrangers, who haue reſpected nothing, but the preſent time, and ſupplying of wants, not caring what became of her hereafter, nor how deformed they made her for to welcome her owne parents: For they cut downe her Woods, euen before Franckendale, and other places, to preuent annoyance from the Enemy, who kept in the ſame as vnder ſhelter, and from thence made many ſallyes vpon the people, and lay as it were in Ambuſcado to ſurpriſe the Souldiers: they ouer-trampled her Vines, and made the hoofes of their Horſes ſpeake cruelly to the rootes: they digged vp her fields for Trenches and Bulwarks: they pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe their houſes round about their Townes to raiſe rauelings and counterſcarps, they oppreſſed the people, ſuffering no man to enioy his owne, nor to giue it away to whom they pleaſed: ſo that they which before in a manner liued ſecurely without walls, and fortifications, are not now ſafe within walls, trenches, and the mounting of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23086:7"/>and this is the miſery of diſcention, and the rage of Princes, who will not be pacified without miſchiefe and reuenge, as is apparant all ouer Bohemia, and thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where the Enemies haue come in with the ſound of hoſtility: ſo that if any demand, why Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſtrong, ſo well prouided, and befriended, doth not returne into the Palatinate, and either contriue the rendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or proſecute the Enemies expulſion. I anſwer plainly: 1. The Souldiers loue the ſpoile better then pay, and ſo are kept together with the hopes of reward, and enriching themſelues. 2. Secondly, the Palatinate being thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, will not ſupply the wants of ſo great an Army. 3. Thirdly, they muſt be conſumed againſt fortified tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Sconſes: For they will not come to a maine bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell except they liſt. 4. Fourthly, treaſure being waſted, he is not ſure alwaies to pay them, and it is a rule in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall diſcipline, not to let the Souldier want, while he lieth in the field. 5. For all his Excellency be thus forward, yet is he ſubiect to direction, and expecteth more friends. 6. Laſt of all, to expulſe the Spaniard &amp; Bauarian by force out of the Palatinate, muſt coſt a great effuſion of blood, and Princes that are good, would ſpare the liues of their Subiects, yea, of Chriſtian Enemies as much as may be. But to returne where we left.</p>
            <p>About the 21. of Nouember, the Enemy approched Dieteſhen with 8000. horſe and foot, and foure Peeces of Ordnance, notwithſtanding Captaine <hi>Banbierg</hi> deſiſted from oppoſing or fighting with him, as pretending he had no ſuch Commiſſion, but only to ſtay for his Excellencies comming, who was reſolued to encounter with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but the Enemy taried in no place, but rather retired backe, and ſo there was no hunting him in a depopulated Countrey. The 25. of Nouemb, his Excellency left Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derberg,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23086:8"/>leauing but one Company, as a Gariſon therein, and marched with all his forces toward Gernſham, and the next day toward Dieteſhen, with foure Peeces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of 15. pound bullet, where the Enemy and he skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed: for though they retired about the 22. of Nouemb. yet they ſtill houered here about, and reſolued vpon any aduantage or opportunity to beſiege the Towne, by which occaſion when we found them here, we came to blowes: but their maine forces lay entrenched by a Marſh, and kept the faſtneſſe, ſo that we could neither enforce them, nor fight any ſet battaile: wherefore his Excellency loath to looſe time in the euening, retired to Bernſhem againe, whereby the Enemy had leaſure to beſiege Dieteſhen, and ſo with nine dayes battery, and the loſſe of 200. men, he tooke it by compoſition, after we (as I ſaid) had skirmiſhed with them the 26. and 27. many times.</p>
            <p>The 29. of Nouemb, the Burgomaſter <hi>Nonnelts</hi> of Spiers was ſent vnto his Excellency with gratification and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they would take vp 1000. men, and giue them three moneths pay, and ſo ſend them well furniſhed to his Excellency, by which example the Townes of Landaw, Weiſenburch, and Hagenaw haue done the like, according to proportion of Inhabitants: but <hi>Strasbourg</hi> hath beat vp the Drums for 4000. with her Villages, who are ready to come vnto vs: ſo that we encreaſe daily, and finde the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to their power, willing to ſupply vs with men, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and munition; whereupon we returned to Dieteſhen againe, and repoſſeſſed the place, putting the Enemy out, and ſo left 300. men as a Gariſon in the ſame, which was done the 12. of Decemb. we did the like to Fridelſhem, but that fell into the Enemies hand, as ſoone as we departed: For you muſt know, that theſe places are neither fortified, nor walled, but as the ſtronger forces poſſeſſe them, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23086:8"/>make them ſeruiceable to their vſes.</p>
            <p>The 16. of December wee marched from Bernſhen to Hagenaw, and ſo to Wantzenaw by Strasburch, and at laſt tooke Elſaz-ſauoren without any great hurt; but moſt chiefly we forraged the whole Biſhoprick to the ſupplying our wants, and enriching the Souldiers. For when <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> vnderſtood what was done, and that we were going away with the ſpoiles; they ſent vnto vs, and redeemed the ſame with the disburſing of 200000. Ricks dollers; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Souldiers full of money and courage, cryed out for the Rhine, and the riuer of Maine: For we now muſtered 16000. foot, and 6000. Horſe, hauing honeſt and probable certificate, that the Bauarians and Spaniards were not 14000. and ſo ſtood in feare of his Excellencies comming vpon them, which no queſtion he would haue done, like thunder, if they would any manner of way had endured the triall, but they had learnt the tricke of entrenching, and ſo expected the good houre of ſupplying their Armies both from Sauoy and Italy.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Ianuary Monſieur <hi>Bonni Court,</hi> a Baron of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, came to Hagenaw to his Excellency with 600. horſe and the Baron <hi>Bouo</hi> with 4000. foote, ſo that it ſhould ſeeme his Excellency is much feared in Loraine: For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Companies haue already taſted the fruits of the Countrey, and with reciprocall gentleneſſe been welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt them, yea, it is certaine, that France her ſelfe ſuſpects his approch, and the Proteſtants euery where pray for his ſucceſſe, and comming amongſt them, becauſe it is rumoured, that the King of France hath taken the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to ouer-runne them all.</p>
            <p>Thus is the muſtring of Souldiers, and taking vp of men on all ſides: for as his Excellency encreaſeth his Company with the inhabitants of Loraine, who willingly ſuffer his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23086:9"/>Muſter-maſters among them, and hath at leaſt 1000. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of Spiers likewiſe to attend his ſeruice: ſo doe the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarians &amp; Spaniards ſeeke daily to augment their troopes, and beſides great hopes out of Italy and Sauoy, haue the helpe and aſſiſtants of the Catholike Biſhops, Princes, Gentlemen, and Townes: ſo that the Earle <hi>George van Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſten</hi> hath taken vp a Regiment of foote, and 600. horſe, who all lye in and about Landaw. Colonell <hi>Tilley</hi> quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with 500. men by and in Landeburg, &amp; hath his other troopes diſpierſed in ſeuerall places: For ſome 14. dayes ſince, he tooke Wimphen, and as we heard many of Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberg retired themſelues to Mainhem, being full of feare, that in the abſence of Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> the Bauarians would come backe againe to Heidelberg it ſelfe, but wee hope it is too ſtrong and well peopled for them, and they dare not as yet leaue the other places wherein they abide, naked and abandoned: beſides, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired ſo farre, but he can come againe vpon them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent further miſchiefe: for Captaine <hi>Cheuit</hi> lying in Dielſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg about the end of December, tooke in a little Towne by the meanes of a playing Petard, and ſlew many of the Bauarians, ſpoiling and burning the place: yet did yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our Colonell <hi>Landſhat,</hi> who is a natiue of that Countrey.</p>
            <p>In this manner are all theſe Countries turmoyled, and the people in Armes, ſo that his excellency groweth ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſtronger, and the Palatinate is much comforted, and expecteth a faire recouery: For in Heidelberg lyeth Colonell <hi>Merſen</hi> as Gouernour, and hath foure Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in his Regiment; with him is ioyned Colonell <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhat</hi> with foure Companies, and two Engliſh Companies, who are well appointed, and the Generall <hi>Vere</hi> is very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and induſtrious, that the Bauarians take him not at any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23086:9"/>aduantage; whereupon Franckendale was alſo newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, ſo that there are now in it 12. Companies, beſides, the Burgers and many hundreds of Peſants, who ſerue for Pyoners, and to ſet forward the workes: nay, they are ſo ſtrong and cheerefull, that they ſent a conuoy with diuers Gentlemen, and well appointed Companies of foot to conduct the Palſgraue Corne &amp; Wine out of Attenbergs: Schonauer and Niewhauſen hoof, with other places, which belonged to his Royalties, to bring all ſafe to Francken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale: but they of Wormes denied vs paſſage, and ſhut their gates, keeping their Sconſes againſt vs, becauſe they pretended a treaty and capitulation with the Bauarians, and either durſt not yeeld to our requeſts, or were indeed diſaffected to vs in their hearts: whereupon Generall <hi>Vere</hi> not thinking it meete to endure ſuch neutrality, or giue way to affronts, which might diſparage his Honour; ſent vs Commiſſion to malepriſe all the commodities, and Marchandize, that came from Wormes, and intercept the Wagons of all ſorts, that paſſed and repaſſed too and from them; whereby we quickly tooke 100. Fats of Wine, much Corne, Horſes, and many other commodities, teaching them a better leſſon of friendlineſſe and conſtancie: ſo that euer ſince they haue agreed, and bound themſelues to be more ſeruiceable, and at that time bought out their Corne and Wine againe at reaſonable rates, though with great loſſe to the Marchant, who in the bargain disburſed 1000. Dollers extraordinary, which were deuided amongſt the Souldiers, who brought themſelues and that they went for quietly to Franckendale.</p>
            <p>After this, we grew bolder and bolder, and made diuers out-roades and in-roades into the Biſhoprick of Spiers, where we obtained good booty, and faw the miſery of theſe places, which were preyed vpon on all ſides, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23086:10"/>made ſubiect to the vſurpation of ſtrangers, who were not dainty to diſrobe her of her beſt ornaments: For as I ſaid before euen at Franckendale it ſelfe, we were enforced to cut downe the goodly Woods round about it, and many thouſand trees in other places, becauſe they ſerued only as a ſhelter for the Spaniards to lye in Ambuſcado, and ſo breake vpon vs vnawares; or if you will lye continually ſhooting at vs to our great loſſe and hinderance, without any endemnity to themſelues: but now God be thanked it is otherwiſe, though to the Countries damage and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and we are preparing for to raiſe out-works, and caſt rafts and trenches, which will queſtionleſſe put the Enemy to great loſſe and trouble to winne, and demoliſh, before he can come neere our Townes: and in this eſtate ſtandeth the Palatinate it ſelfe at this houre, both our ſelues and the Enemy well fortified in euery place, and reſolued, that if they come not to an orderly rendition, it will be now a matter of great difficulty, to put the poſſeſſors out of their holds and fortifications, eſpecially if the Souldiers be well paid, and take notice of the Officers care to ſupply their wants: For although the Countrey be much forraged, yet for money prouiſion will come on all ſides, and the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers can ſend downe their Boats and Punts from remoter places, with corne, cattell, wine, and other neceſſaries, as occaſion ſhall ſerue.</p>
            <p>While we thus buſied our ſelues in the Palatinate, and lay watching one another to preuent the miſchiefes, which might be taken vpon aduantages, his Excellency grew ſtronger and ſtronger, and had planted himſelfe as it were in a new Countrey: whereupon the ſpirituality of Mentz, and the confines of Loraine, yea ſome ſay of Metts like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, deſired with one conſent a truce for two moneths, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expecting reliefe, which I know not from whence it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23086:10"/>ſhould come, or reſoluing to buy out their peace, which is that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> deſired, as knowing money to be the very ſinewes of his ſtrength, and binding cords to keepe all ſtrongly together, or fearing his forces and proteſtations: For concerning the one, they ſaw apparantly, that as the Scriptures ſaid of <hi>Iehu,</hi> he came or marched furiouſly: ſo did this Champion of Honor, whirle vp and downe their Countries with violence, and added forces to forces to firme himſelfe the ſtronger. Concerning the other, ſeeing the Spaniards and Bauarians had led him the way, and taught him a leſſon of intruſion, and vſurping another mans right; why ſhould not he doe the like, paying them with their owne money, and prizing the ballances with their owne weights? nay, if they were ſo ready to rob and ſpoile the Proteſtants in the Palatinate? why ſhould not hee be as willing and propence to forrage the Papiſts, whereſoeuer they recided, or he could finde them. Theſe conſiderations made the Biſhops and other Clergy men ſuſpect their eſtates, and reſolue to compound for their quietneſſe: For as I ſaid, they ſaw no forces ready either to oppoſe or expell the Mansfildians, as I may call them, nor could indeed coniecture, what would be the ſucceſſe of theſe affaires, or whether this glorious Army would march, much leſſe in what attempts it might be proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. For they ſaw plainely the Biſhoprick of Spiers was ſpoiled, and that the Towne it ſelfe had agreed with him, and in a manner promiſed, not to entertaine any Spaniſh Catiſons, though <hi>Don Cordona</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned the ſame: yet for all this did the Biſhop retire with certaine Cornets of Horſe to Idenheim, where Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> was reſident, and his Excellency perceiuing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts onely to temporiſe, was the vnwillinger to come to any compoſition with them, but would rather aduenture
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23086:11"/>on the ſpoile: but at laſt his reſolution was to be contented with ſo much money ready paid.</p>
            <p>You haue heard before, that there was ſome contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betweene the Spaniards and Bauarians about points of honour, or (if you will) tumors of vaine-glory and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, which now burſt out againe: For about the 7. of Ianuary, while the Bauarians were reſolued to attempt ſome places: <hi>Don Cordoua</hi> againſt all expectation would endure the field no longer, nor hazard his Souldiers in the extremity of Winter, which now came vpon them, and ſo retired himſelfe to Winter his troopes in better lodging; whereby wee had the more leaſure to ſurpriſe ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, as paſſed to and fro the Countrey: yea, his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency commanded the Rhine at Germſhem, and had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Ships and Boats ready either to make a Bridge ouer the ſame, or to tranſport his Army and Prouiſion to ſuch places, as he determined to lodge in: but he went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently as you heard into the Biſhoprick of Mentz, and they of Strasburg gaue liberty to his Captaines to muſter men, and take vp SOuldiers in his name, though the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> had ſent an Ambaſſadour to diuers Townes by way of countermaund and prohibition: But alas! Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies will doe no good, where men are Maſters of the field, and Armies lye ready to proſecute any tyranny contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or in the heat of fury and reuenge: For ſuch was the ſucceſſe of Earle <hi>Mansfields</hi> affaires, that he tooke vp men in all places, and ſo went directly to Elſas, a Towne of great expectation: for although ſome two moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had poſſeſſion of the ſame, as he thought, hauing receiued ſome Souldiers into the Towne, whereby it was confidently giuen out, that Elſas, or Elſas Saueren was his owne, being a fortified place, ſubiect to the Archduke <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paldus,</hi> who is Lord of that Countrey they call <hi>Alſatia,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23086:11"/>betweene Switzerland and Mentz, arriuing by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of Spiers, and the Palatinate, full of Riuers, and extraordinary commodities, and euery way conuenient for his Excellencies affaires: yet they reuolted againe, and put out all his gariſons, ſtanding firme for their owne Lord the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus:</hi> ſo that much exaſperated againſt them, about the 17. of Ianuary, he ſent moſt part of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my either to beſiege or ſurpriſe it, who in the march tooke all the Biſhops Booers, with their Horſes and Waggons, and made good booty.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further, you muſt conſider, that in all your Dutch Currantoes, this word <hi>Elſas</hi> is taken for the whole Countrey of <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> as much as for the Towne it ſelfe, and therefore may bring confuſion to the Reader, that he ſuppoſeth ſometimes the Country is taken, when it is but the Towne, and the Towne is taken, when he is onely marching in the Countrey. Another error ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from theſe Currantoes in confuſion of time, by <hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> yea by many antidates, and poſtdates, ſo that they place that firſt, which ſhould be laſt, and that laſt, which had a paſſage of former time. Thirdly, that they build too much vpon heare-ſayes and reports, and ſo truſting vnto various opinions, huddle all newes together, becauſe they would be thought to know ſomething. Laſt of all, your Dutch Letters haue a ſtrange cuſtome of partiality to ſet out the glory, and renowne of their owne Countrey-men, and ſcarce to mention either the Engliſh, or any other Nation, who are indeed the beſt Actors in ſuch ſeruices: As for example, in the diſcription of the fiege of <hi>Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> not an Engliſh-man in any Curranto, or Dutch Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is named: but onely Captaine <hi>Ouertrant,</hi> and ſuch like, when yet the Engliſh deſerued better then any Nation. Againe: in the gouernment of Heidelberg, onely the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23086:12"/>Dutch Gouernour is commended, but the Engliſh are ſparingly paſt ouer, with naming of two Engliſh Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the Towne: Nay, in the deſcription of Mainhem it ſelfe, the Generall <hi>Vere</hi> is ſlightly charactered, when yet by commiſſion from the King of Bohemia, he is the great Commaunder of the whole Countrey; and Count <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> himſelfe, while he is reſident there, muſt acknowledge his authority. Theſe thinges I thought good to certifie you of by way of tranſition, that you bee not altogether tranſported with Dutch newes, and partiality, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with tranſmutation of time and names, nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with any relation, which ſhall ſeeme to darken the glory of theſe affaires, or the hope of better ſucceſſe in the Palatinate buſines. But to auoyde all doubts, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and oppoſitions, I haue (gentle Reader) for your ſake compoſed this diſcourſe, and in a plaine phraſe, that you may rely vpon one truth, and teach your hearts a ſong of thankeſgiuing to the God of truth, and battailes, that hath thus begun to bring matters about, againſt all expectation: and ſo to our buſineſſe againe.</p>
            <p>In Lotringhem the Spaniards Commiſſaries, as well as Earle <hi>Mansfields,</hi> met to take vp men, and muſter Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and were very iealous one of another, who ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in their greater numbers, how they ſped I cannot tell, but we were pleaſed in our accounts: For although diuers went to Elnſhiſem to ſerue Duke <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> with aſſurance that more would follow: yet we made a ſtrong party, and marched forward with 16. peeces of Ordinance, &amp; leauing 300. men in Germerſheim, tooke our way to Lanterbergh, where wee had a great skirmiſh, and loſt ſome men, not without reciprocall damage to the Enemy: but before we paſſed from hence, newes came of the Spaniards comming to Germerſheim, with reſolution to make a ſhip Bridge
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23086:12"/>there, and that 600. Bauarian Souldiers were gone out vpon booty, whom we watched narrowly to catch in their returne, but we failed at this time, and were croſſed againe with a new report, that the Towne of Spiers had entertained 1000. Souldiers to defend the ſame, as ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting we might come thither, and take them at ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: and thus were the Catholike Biſhops likewiſe ſtanding on their guards, and neither went abroad without a conuoy, nor ſlept in their Pallaces without Courts of guard; nay, the alarum went as farre as Cullein, and all places prepared to delend themſelues: for the Papiſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> reſolued to draw the warre from the Palatinate, into the Biſhops Countries, and were in great feare, that the young Duke of Brunſwick with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Lords, in the behalfe of the King of Bohemia, would make a ſtrong party on the other ſide of the Rhine, as well as Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> had done on this ſide toward Loraine, and the borders of France.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Ianuary, wee tooke in the Towne and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Hagenaw, reſoluing to quarter our ſelues there, and ſo remained quiet a while, till his Excellency reſolued to proſecute the fiege of Elſas Saberen more throughly, ſuppoſing that, as the Archduke <hi>Deopoldus</hi> kept there his Court of Chancery, he had alſo beene there in perſon, but the truth was, he had not long ſince retired himſelfe into the Valtolina. In briefe: after we had diſarmed all the Souldiers that were in the Townes, we tooke, ſpoiled the lewes, and forraged the Countries, as turning our ſelues round about without any certaine paſſage forward, or backward. Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſent Colonell <hi>Ouertrant</hi> as Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of this new Army, with 3000. foot, and 1000. Horſe, ſeauen peeces of Cannon, ſome Petards, and many Pyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Workmen, who ſeated themſelues before the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23086:13"/>Towne, making large quarters, and yet fortifying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues after the cuſtome of trenched Camps: the firſt thing they doe, was the ſummoning the place to the vſe of Count <hi>Mansfield;</hi> the next thing they attempted, was the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame, as farre as demolition, if they did not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſurrender and compound for their quietneſſe. They of the Towne demaunded three dayes reſpite: they of the Campe murmured at the delay, whereupon <hi>Onertrant</hi> ſent a meſſenger to his Excellency to know his reſolution; who remembring former grieuances, and exaſperated for their firſt reuolt, ſent 1000. men more with a ſeuere impoſition, not to allow them three houres by way of diſputing, except they determined at the time prefixed to yeeld indeed: for haue it he would, whatſoeuer it coſt him. In the meane while all the Biſhopricks were ſpoiled, and the Papiſts had not now ſo great a cauſe of ioy and triumph, as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning their oſtentation ſhewed.</p>
            <p>So that I will be bolde to ſay, neuer was ſuch an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For though Prague is in poſſeſſion of the Emperour, who hath wracked his rage vpon ſuch he named Traytors, and the Palatinate is thus ſorraged by the Bauarians and our Souldiers. Yet marke what followed, euen in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the deuaſtation of all Germany, and the Papiſts euery where are ſet vpon by the Proteſtants, &amp; our Enemies op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with as great Armies and forces: For how the Duke of Saxony is turmoiled in Sileſia, and his owne Countrey is apparant, ſo that in my conſcience he wiſheth an end of the Warre. The Hungarians forrage euen Sileſia it ſelfe, and ſpare none, who haue beene oppoſite to the King of Bohemia. <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> takes it ill, that the Emperour will raiſe Souldiers out of Poland to diſturbe his friends, and ſo procured the Turke to ſend a Chauſe vnto him, to certifie his pleaſure of miſliking the ſame; and withall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23086:13"/>watcheth Morauis, and thoſe parts. Generall <hi>Ieggendorff</hi> followeth <hi>Don Baltaſer</hi> at the heeles, and ſent word to Count <hi>Mrnsfield,</hi> that if he would returne into Auſtria, now the Emperour was gone to Inſpurg, they would or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the matter ſo to intercept his returning to Vienna. The young Duke of Brunſwick hath plaid alſo his Maſters priſe againſt the Biſhop of Haluerſtat, who hath forſaken his Countrey to looke for ſhelter in other places: ſo that the Elector of Montz was compelled to fortifie Amenburg, and put a Bauarian Gariſon in the ſame: yea, ſuch is the turmoile of theſe Countries, that no place is free of of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance, nor perſon aſſured of his eſtate: For the Prince ELectors are ſo iealous of theſe affaires, that as farre as they durſt, they called the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Heſs in queſtion, for permitting the Duke of Brunſwick to come ſo farre and peaceably into his Countrey vnrefiſted, and ſought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: but he neither denied it, nor they durſt proſecute the matter. To conclude Prague it ſelfe, the Emperour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing baniſhed all the Procoſtant Miniſters, and proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them Traytors, who ſhall any way affiſt them, is ready to muteny, and the Gariſons that keepe them in awe, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect one another, and the reuolt of the place, if euer there come an Army before it.</p>
            <p>While theſe things haue their ſeuerall paſſages in the remoter places, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> proſecuteth his determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt Elſas Saueren, and the whole Countrey of the Archduke <hi>Leopaldus,</hi> ſo that diuers Swiſs haue offered him their ſeruice, and the Archduke is much moleſted to ſee ſuch a fire raiſed againſt him: whereupon by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Strasburgs inticement, he ſent three perſons of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by the way of an Ambaſſie, that if he would leaue the Dioceſſe of Strasburg, and his Countrey vnmoleſted, he would reſtore the Veltolina againe, and make a perfect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23086:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:23086:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:23086:15"/>peace with the Heſuetians. Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> replied, he muſt haue other compoſition, ere he deſiſted what was his owne, or knew he could make his owne, he would keepe vntill the Palatinate were reſtored, and the Bauarians and Spaniards departed, he would either diuert the Warre to other places, or enrich his Army out of other mens purſes: as for the name of peace, it had an ill accent in theſe times, confidering their owne examples: For what did he any more then was taught him, and could he doe leſſe, then ſet on foot ſome reuenge. If the Spaniards and Bauarians vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of the Emperours ſeruice, had ſet vpon the Palatinate, and Proteſtants there, the auncient inheritance of a religious Prince, and Elector of the Empire: why might not he for the ſeruice of the King of Bohemia i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Countries, who were irreligious Papiſts, and held thoſe Diabolicall poſitions of murthering, and depoſing of Princes.</p>
            <p>This anſwer was much diſpleaſing to <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> but he ſaw no remedy. For to adde vnto his diſcontentment, the Switzers reſolued not to admit of his gouernment, and ſo ſent word to the Duke of Millane of the ſame, who could doe nothing without the King of Spaines reſolutions: but they would not tarry his anſwer, but ſought all the meanes they could to free themſelues, and aſſiſt the Grizons for the recouery of the Valtolina againe: whereupon they certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> of all their affaires, who reſolued to follow <hi>Leopoldus</hi> whether ſoeuer he went, and to preſſe him to make an end of the Warre, and that intruſion.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, the Towne of Elſas is now befieged, and the three dayes they demaunded, expired, ſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo lued to fight it out, and ſent word to the Caſtle of He genbart, ſtanding vpon a very high rock, to annoy the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as they could, which they did night and day: For the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23086:15"/>Mansfildians lay within ſhot, and the Towne thought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nothing but reſcue: but neither did the Artillery doe any great harme to the Army, nor could <hi>Leopoldus</hi> preuent the miſchiefe which followed: For about the 27. of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Army gaue a braue affault vpon the Towne, and with diuers batteries, and the loſſe of 400. men, with two principall Captaines, they tooke the ſame, as alſo Mours Menſter, where were ſlaine 300: but in both they found ſufficient riches, with 300. Tunne of Wine, and many thouſand meaſures of Corne, but neither ſpoile, not rapes were committed: For vpon ſmall payments their houſes ſtood with their Houſhold-ſtuffe and Vtenſels vnſtirred, and none were ranſommed, but the honeſt Papiſts: For the Abbot and diuers others, were faine to flye, and diſpierce themſelues into Lotteringhen, and ſundry places of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: yet could not preuent great disburſements of mony, nor in a manner ranſomming themſelues: For the Mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue of Tourlack tooke his Excellencies part, and got ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people and Souldiers to be retained in his Excellencies Army, which was muſtred anew, and ſo he marched backe againe toward Loraine with all the Peeces, which he had at Hagenaw, who were faine to diſburſe 10000. ricks dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to buy out their peace; yea, the Duke of Lottinghem himſelfe came to a compoſition of 100000. ricks dollers, that he would paffe quietly without forraging his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which order he obſerueth with all the places, that doe quietly ſurrender; as for thoſe that oppoſe againſt him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Village or Towne he leaueth to the ſpoile of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and when they haue no ſpoile, he payeth them out of his treaſury.</p>
            <p>Now you muſt conſider, that how euer Elſas Saueren was taken, yet there was a compoſition made, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of agreement ratified betweene them for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23086:16"/>of 300000. Ricks dollers, which were demanded the firſt of February, and for want of disburſing, much vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and threatning followed: yet had they fine dayes lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſpite: in which interim Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> retiring himſelfe to Hagenaw, gaue the Army leaue to viſite the Countrey, and ſuch places where they might imagine any booty was to be gotten, or Enemy to be met withall: and ſo about the third of February 9. Cornets of Horfe paſſed Strasburag Bridge to intercept the Bauarians, who were gone vpon ſome deſigne to Swatwood: And vpon the fourth of-February many Companies went out another way, and burned foure of the Biſhops Villages, watching the Markets, and taking many Bauarians priſoners, who lye vpon the Countrey; as well as themſelues, and take one another at aduantage, as opportunity feiues their turnes. The fift of February the ſpeech was, that the whole Army would riſe and march forward to Hemſes Heim, Brifac, and Friburg: but hearing that the Bauarians were going to new lodging, they deſiſted for that time, and did not meane to ſtirre, till they were aſſured where the Enemy would diſpoſe of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>While theſe things were ſhowne on the Stage of Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and all Chriſtiandome ſtood looking on to behold, what ſcenes theſe ſeruants of Bellona would act: Letters both of gratification and direction came from the King of Denmark, and all that fauoured the cauſe of the Palatinate, wherein he had particular intelligence, that the Proteſtant Princes were reſolued vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an Army of their own, that is to ſay, to be paid at their owne charges, vnder the commaund of the Earle of Tourlach, and to that purpoſe <hi>Murterbergh</hi> taketh vp 3000. Foot, and 500. Horſe: the Barrons <hi>Meſſairs de Bounoies,</hi> and <hi>Frandecount,</hi> two Regiments, the <hi>Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>graue</hi> of Baden, and Duke <hi>Weymaren</hi> 3000. Foot, and 500. Horſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23086:16"/>Duke <hi>Magnus</hi> 1000. foot, and 400. horſe, <hi>Hemſteder</hi> 3000 foot, the <hi>Rheien Graf Oue</hi> 500. horſe, <hi>Fleckenſteine</hi> 600. horſe, and <hi>Golſtein</hi> 3000. foot, and 400. horſe: all which with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others ſhall march vnder the ſtandard of the Princes of the Vnion: For although they vnderſtand of great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations from Sauoy, Naples, Millaine, Spaine, Poland, Auſtria, and the Princes combined vnto the Emperour and his ſeruice: yet they are aſſured that the Switzers haue leagued themſelues, both Proteſtants and Papiſts to caſt off the yoke of the Spaniſh gouernment, and to moue in their owne free Orbes, as they did before: yea, <hi>Leopald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doth much repine at the Spaniards intruſion into the Valtolina, or any territories of the Grizons for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, did euer belong vnto a younger houſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, and one of the Archdukes in former times loſt his life about the ſame, and with much adoe it was obtained.</p>
            <p>And thus much of Earle <hi>Mansfields</hi> proceedings, to the 12. of February laſt, whoſe comming downe into the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, beſides the running away ſo fortunately with his owne actions, hath made the paſſage the caſier for Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Veres</hi> care and diligence to fortifie ſuch principall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as lay open before to the daring approches of a ſtrong Enemy, and the fearefull batteries of a Cannon, or other ſtratagems of Warre: but now Heidelberg with many other Townes are well fortified, the paſſages haue Scon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: the confines are garriſond, the riuers haue Bridges, which they can take away at their pleaſure, and the very Boores, though labouring like Pyoners, returne to their Villages with the reputation of a Souldier: ſo that in my conſcience, if <hi>Spinola</hi> himſelfe were now to take poſſeſſion into this Countrey, he would finde it more difficult, then he did, and whoſoeuer may conceit by the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that therefore the Bauarian and Spaniard, being
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23086:17"/>now fortified, will hardly be compulſed out without ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or compoſition. I anſwer plainely, I thinke ſo to: For ſo I am aſſured the behalfe of the Bauarians, that they will hardly get any further places of account, then they haue: but if the Warre be diuerted to other Countries, as you ſaw, how the Romanes dealt with <hi>Anniball,</hi> to draw him to defend Carthage, that had been 17. yeares in Italy, and could not be ſtartled from thence by force, or pollicy, then it may be theſe intruders will be glad to goe home againe to keepe their Countrey from the cruell Armes of deuaſtation: or if ſome thundring troopes come vpon them, with a well diſciplined and gouerned Army, then may the ſtronger arme put out the ſtrong man.</p>
            <p>As for their obiection, that would commend the piety of the Enemy, in not ouer-running the Countrey at his firſt entrance into it. What hath hee done better then Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath done in many Countries? but I will anſwer more particularly; peraduenture he could not, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Noble <hi>Vere</hi> came to intercept his forwardnes: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture he was willing to taſte of the Grapes and fruits many dayes, and then it had beene folly to haue made an vntimely Vintage, and deuoured all in one day. Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture he was loath to goe too farre, for looſing himſelfe in a Wood, or hazard his returne when he would, if ſuch came behind him, as would make him leape ouer their Pikes, or peraduenture he had limitation, leaſt by prouing too cruell, he might ſtop vp the gap of all piety and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration, if euer the wheele of Fortune would turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and leaue the triumpher himſelfe in the hands of compaſſion, as in all ages and chances of Warre hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, where many a time the Sonne hath beene ſtabbed for his Fathers cruelty, &amp; the Generall reconciled, by find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a noble aduerſary. But here me thinks I am anſwered with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23086:17"/>peremptorineſſe, that theſe Countries haue ſuch mighty aduerſaries, that there is no poſſibility of extenuating their greatneſſe, much leſſe of bringing them to the barre of a new examination.</p>
            <p>Be not too preſumptuous, nor runne away ſo faſt with ouer-confidence of any worldly ſtability: remember rather what <hi>Mordecay</hi> ſaid to <hi>Heſter:</hi> That if ſhe did not goe in to the King for the preſeruation of her people, God would raiſe ſome help another way to bring his purpoſes to paſſe: ſo ſay I of the Palatinate, when we runne away with an opinion of inuincible Armados, and for euitable Armies: the windes and weather may diſcipate the one, and very weake oppoſition, ouerthrow the other. For the God of windes and battailes, hath a trick to humble vs with hard beginnings at the firſt; that proſperity may be the better welcome, when it is hammered out (as it were) on the Anuill of toile, trauaile, wants, diſgrace, contempt, and other fearefull endurances.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
